DC Oral History Collaborative Collection 180
People's Archive, MLK Library
- Series 10: Oral History of DanceAfrica, D.C., 2018
  - Sub-Series 1: Interviews, 2018
    - Sylvia Soumah interview, 2018-05-18
      In this oral history Sylvia Soumah reflects on her young life growing up in a Cincinnati, Ohio housing project, falling in love with dance, and building her career in dance in Washington, D.C. In Cincinnati she attended a performing arts high school, upon graduation she worked at a German restaurant, until, at age 20, she left for Washington D.C. While waitressing in Adams Morgan, she began dancing, initially dancing mostly modern and jazz. She talks about discovering African styles of dance initially because the classes where a friendly place for her to bring her child, then instantly becoming hooked and shifting her focus. She first performed at DanceAfrica in 1992. Her love for African dance inspires her to travel to Guinea. She speaks about how she never expected her career to take off, at first her dances focused on issues that were very personal to her. She eventually started a youth academy. She reflects on how the festival has changed a lot, and how the Brookland neighborhood, in which her studio is embedded, has changed.
    - Melvin Deal interview, 2018-05-14
      Melvin Deal has been an integral part of the Washington, D.C. African dance community for over five decades. He is a Washington, D.C. native that started dancing in 1959. He graduated from Howard University in 1965. His contributions include having trained countless at-risk youth in dance, residencies at all the major Washington, D.C. area universities, helping to found the Duke Ellington School for the Arts, and work with the DanceAfrica festival.
      "Melvin Deal reflects on his work performing, choreographing, managing, and promoting African dance, which he has been involved in for over half a century. He speaks about how when he started dancing it was generally understood that you had to do ballet, if you wanted to be successful. But he was drawn to African dance and decided to follow that desire. At the time, decolonization was happening in Africa. Part of his work was fighting stereotypes about Africa. He reflects that at the time they were being romantic about being Africans. His interests brought him to take his first trip to Africa in 1969. Many of his former students were at-risk youths that credit him with having changed the direction of their lives. Through his African Heritage dancers, he won legitimacy for African culture in the community and the larger city. He speaks about educating a Washington Post writer about Africa dance and how the resulting articles led to a large uptick in attendance at African dance events. He expresses concerned about young people's sense of personhood, "I feel like I am someone now", is the feeling he wants young people to feel."
    - Baile McKnight interview, 2018-05-17
      Baile McKnight is a drummer who drums in African traditions. He has been active in African dance and drumming circles in Washington, D.C., and beyond, for over five decades. He grew-up in Washington, D.C., often traveling to spend time with family in North Carolina.
      In this interview Baile McKnight reflects on his life and the important role that African drumming has plaid in it. He talks about how having close connections to family in North Carolina, while growing up in Washington, D.C., and made Baile aware of cultural differences. Travel and the importance of culture plays a major role in his narrative. Another major point of emphasis is his visit to Africa. He feels that his visits to Nigeria played a major role in helping him to understand African drumming. The history of slavery and the slave trade is another important contributing factor to the cultures of dance and drumming that he believes is important for people to be aware of. McKnight speaks about changes to Washington, D.C. including his observations about displacement in the city. Training and mastery are key elements for drummers that he speaks about. He feels that artists free people's minds and helps to heal their trauma.
    - Makini Niliwambieni interview, 2018-05-21
      Makini Niliwambieni a.k.a. Mama Makin grew up in Trenton, NJ, where she began to study and perform African styles of dance as part of a revival in interests in African cultures that grew alongside the civil rights movement. In 1989 she moved to Washington, D.C., where she continues to choreograph, teach, and perform African styles of dance.
      Makini Niliwambieni a.k.a. Mama Makini reflects on her life and what brought her to dedicate decades to performing, choreographing, and teaching African styles of dance. She talks about growing-up in Trenton, NJ, where she was exposed to "Black Arts" coming out of the Civil Rights Movement. She first started attending African Dance classes as part of the African People's Action School, which was closely related to the socialist All African People Revolutionary Party founded by Kwame NKrumah of Ghana. She speaks about her children and how they enjoyed dance to various degrees. She says her youngest daughter could remember dance moves better than her. She also speaks about her first impressions of Washington, D.C. and how she liked the slower pace of D.C. compared to the New York / Trenton Area. Mama Makini talks about why she likes to choreograph and work with young people. She also discusses how she got into religion, particularly sanatoria, and why she thinks it is important for African-Americans to get a sense of identity from Africa.
    - Akua Kouyate-Tate interview, 2018-08-13
      Akua Kouyate-Tate is Vice President of Education at Wolf Trap Center for the performing Arts. She grew-up in Washington, D.C. and attended D.C. Public Schools. She then attended Boston University, and earned a BA from American University. She has been involved in promoting, performing, and teaching African styles of dance in Washington, D.C. for decades.
      Akua Kouyate speaks about and reflects on the important role that dance has played in her life and the importance of DanceAfrica and other programs that connect African-Americans to traditional and contemporary styles of African dance. She speaks about growing up and going to Washington, D.C. public schools. She discovered AfricanDance at a community organization in Southeast Washington, D.C. She developed her interest in dance while a student at Boston University, and continued to study dance after transferring to American University. She speaks about transitioning to making the arts and dance into a career. She had to learn business management skills, as well as how to be a teacher. She has taught at universities around Washington D.C. Throughout her oral history it is clear that dance has been an integral part of her life. She tries to focus on both traditional and contemporary style of dance because "Culture is not static." Experience traveling in travel and how it shaped her. Believes that African traditions are traditions that African Americans are also born into. For this reason, her family practiced Islam and African and African- American traditions. The youth summer employment program as key to her work as a dance teacher.
    - Assane Konte interview, 2018-08-09
      Assane Konte is the artistic director, choreographer and costume designer and founding member of the KanKouran West African Dance Company. He has toured the world with African Dance groups and taught at Georgetown, Howard University, George Washington, American University, and George Mason University. His professional dance career started in when he joined Ballet Africaine de Diebel Guee in Dakar at age 15. He later moved from Senegal to the United States where he founded KanKouran and continues to perform.
      Assane Konte speaks about the importance that dance has played in his life, growing up in Senegal, and his first impressions of the United States. His life in dance led him to start visiting the United States for dance festivals, which eventually led him to decide to relocate to the U.S. He highlights the importance of hard work and discipline in dancing as well as and how these virtues contribute to other aspects of life. He believes that his upbringing in Senegal helped to teach him these virtues. He has participated in the DanceAfrica festival since its founding in 1987. He speaks about his love for the festival and how it plays an important role in nurturing cultures related to African dance in the U.S.
  - Sub-Series 2: Indexes, 2018
    - Sylvia Soumah interview index, 2018
    - Melvin Deal interview index, 2018
    - Baile McKnight interview index, 2018
    - Makini Niliwambieni interview index, 2018
    - Akua Kouyate-Tate interview index, 2018
    - Assane Konte interview index, 2018
  - Sub-Series 3: transcripts, 2018
    - Sylvia Soumah interview transcript, 2018
    - Melvin Deal interview transcript, 2018
    - Baile McKnight interview transcript, 2018
    - Makini Niliwambieni interview transcript, 2018
    - Akua Kouyate-Tate interview transcript, 2018
    - Assane Konte interview transcript, 2018
- Series 11: Voices of The DC Fort Totten Storytellers Oral History Project, 2018
  This project documents the stories of residents of Fort Totten, Washington, D.C., a neighborhood nestled between Fort Totten Park, the Armed Forces Retirement Home, and Rock Creek Cemetery. Fort Totten is an area in which African Americans began to enjoy equal opportunity in purchasing homes in the 1950s and 1960s. The neighborhood's rowhouses were built by Colony Construction Company in the 1930s, developed by Morris Cafritz, and designed by architect George T. Santmyers.
  African Americans; Fort Totten (Washington, D.C.); Gentrification; Neighborhoods; Childhood and youth
  - Sub-Series 1: Interviews
    - Gale Griffin interview part 1, 2018-04-16
      Written permission from the narrator is required to access this interview.
      Gale Griffin was born in Alexandria, Virginia and moved with her family to Washington, DC when she was six months old. Her family then moved to the Fort Totten neighborhood in 1956 when she was four years old. She talks about the close-knit nature of the Fort Totten community and the long-lasting friendships that formed among neighborhood children. She attended Keene Elementary School, Bertie Backus Junior High School, the new Rabaut Junior High School, and Roosevelt High School. She attended Federal City College for two years. She worked for the postal service for 33 years. She talks about the changes that gentrification has brought both to her current Nicholson Street neighborhood and the Fort Totten area where her mother still resides.
      Gale Griffin discusses the close-knit nature of the Fort Totten community and the long-lasting friendships that formed among neighborhood children. Griffin also discusses the changes that gentrification has brought both to her current Nicholson Street neighborhood and the Fort Totten area where her mother still resides.
    - Gale Griffin interview part 2, 2018-04-16
    - Gale Griffin interview part 3, 2018-04-16
    - Marvin Kirby interview, 2018-06-21
      Marvin Kirby was born in Washington, DC. He moved with his wife and children to the Fort Totten neighborhood in 1964. He attended Bruce Elementary School, Banneker Junior High School, and Cardozo High School. He served two years in the Army and then attended Cortez Peters Business School. He worked for the federal government for several years.
      Marvin Kirby discusses his neighbors and memories of living in the Fort Totten community as well as changes gentrification has brought Fort Totten.
    - Michael Stanley interview, 2018-06-05
      Michael Stanley was born in Washington, DC. His family first lived on Savannah Terrace in Southeast Washington before moving to the Fort Totten neighborhood in 1955. Mr. Stanley attended Keene Elementary School until the sixth grade, MacFarland Middle School, Bertie Backus Middle School, and Theodore Roosevelt High School. Stanley was drafted into the Army where he served for two years and nine months in Vietnam. Upon leaving the military Mr. Stanley attending the University of the District of Columbia, studying business management. Stanley was the Branch Chief for DC Courts.
      Michael Stanley discusses the close-knit Fort Totten neighborhood of his childhood, his summers spent with other children from the neighborhood, his extracurricular school activities and social life as a teenager, and the changes that gentrification has brought to the DC area.
    - Patrice Brown interview, 2018-05-12
      Patrice Brown was born in Washington, DC. As a young child, Ms. Brown and her siblings spent weekdays with their grandparents in the Mount Pleasant neighborhood and weekends with their parents. Ms. Brown attended H.D. Cooke Elementary School and Morgan Elementary School before moving to the Fort Totten neighborhood with her family where she attended Bertie Backus Junior High and Theodore Roosevelt High School. Ms. Brown attended Dumbarton College and The George Washignton Universtity. She is currently an archivist at the National Archives and Records Administration.
      Patrice Brown discusses the important role civic associations have played in making Fort Totten a community and remembers the Orange Hat patrols. She discusses gentrification and the changing demographics of the Fort Totten neighborhood. Ms. Brown also discusses her family's deep roots in the DC metro area.
    - Philip Purvis interview, 2018-08-23
      Philip Purvis was born in Washington, DC in 1955. In 1969, he moved to Woodridge. Following high school, he did go through some tough times with addiction and homelessness. He spent his entire life in Washington and recollects fond memories.
      He talks about his childhood experiences growing up in Fort Totten with his family and friends, remembering past businesses he frequented.
    - Sharon Brown interview, 2018-05-12
      This oral history interview was conducted with Sharon Brown by Stephanie Mills Trice in Washington, DC. Sharon Brown was born at Columbia Hospital in Washington, DC. From kindergarten to sixth grade, she split her time between her grandparent's home in the Mount Pleasant area, where she attended Morgan Elementary and H.D. Cooke, and her family's home in the Fort Totten neighborhood. She attended Backus Junior High and Roosevelt High School. Sharon Brown graduated from Catholic University and worked as nurse for a few years before returning to college to get a degree in information technology and a master's in library science. She has worked as a librarian since. She talks about being a teenager in the quiet and friendly neighborhood of Fort Totten and discusses how gentrification and changing demographics have affected both the Fort Totten community and her church in LeDroit Park.
    - Vannie Kirby interview, 2018-06-21
      This oral history interview was conducted with Vannie Kirby by Stephanie Mills Trice in Washington, DC. Vannie Kirby was born in Rockingham, North Carolina and moved to Washington, DC to attend business school. Mrs. Kirby and her husband moved to the Fort Totten neighborhood in 1964. She talks about raising her children in Fort Totten. She attended Cortez Peters Business School for two years and worked for the Department of Public Health for 31 years. She talks about the changes gentrification has brought to the Fort Totten area where she still resides.
    - Wendell Moore interview part 1, 2018-07-05
      This oral history interview was conducted with Wendell Moore by Jules Johnson in Washington, DC. Wendell Moore was born in Northwest Washington and moved to the Fort Totten neighborhood when he was in fourth grade. He talks about his early memories of playing in the alleys and the woods by Fort Totten with the other neighborhood children. He attended Barnard Elementary, Rabaut Junior High, and Calvin Coolidge Senior High School. Wendell Moore studied business administration at Bowie State University. After graduating, he secured a management position at Giant Food. He continued his education while working and received his master's and PhD. He also works as a professor at Bowie State University. Wendell Moore talks about the demographic changes he's seen throughout Washington, DC over the decades and the importance of being proactive.
    - Wendell Moore interview part 2, 2018-07-05
  - Sub-Series 2: Indexes and Transcripts
    - Gale Griffin interview index, 2018-04-16
    - Gale Griffin interview transcript part 1, 2018-04-16
    - Gale Griffin interview transcript part 2, 2018-04-16
    - Marvin Kirby interview index, 2018-06-21
    - Marvin Kirby interview transcript, 2018-06-21
    - Michael Stanley interview transcript, 2018-06-05
    - Michael Stanley interview index, 2018-06-05
    - Patrice Brown interview index, 2018-05-12
    - Patrice Brown interview transcript, 2018-05-12
    - Philip Purvis interview index, 2018-08-23
    - Philip Purvis interview transcript, 2018-08-23
    - Sharon Brown interview index, 2018-05-12
    - Sharon Brown interview transcript, 2018-05-12
    - Vannie Kirby interview index, 2018-06-21
    - Vannie Kirby interview transcript, 2018-06-21
    - Wendell Moore interview index, 2018-07-05
- Series 12: The Brookland Literary And Hunting Club (BLAHC): It's Not What You Think!, 2018
  This project documents the experiences of the five final members (and one spouse) of the Brookland Literary and Hunting Club (BLAHC), an invitation-only poker and social club founded in the Brookland neighborhood of Washington, DC, in 1942 by nine accomplished Black men — doctors, lawyers, scientists, university presidents — many with Howard University affiliations. Successive generations of BLAHC members gathered monthly for over 75 years to discuss important topics of the day (the 'literary') and to play poker (the 'hunt').
  The Brookland Literary and Hunting Club (BLAHC): It's Not What You Think! Oral history project contains six video interviews conducted by Eve K. Austin and Kenneth Campbell in 2018. Indexes and transcripts are included for all interviews.
  Societies and clubs; Brookland (Washington, D.C.); Poker
  - Sub-Series 1: Interviews, 2018
    - James Butts interview, 2018-04-20
      Jim Butts was born in Louisville, Kentucky in 1934. His parents were hard working and active in the community and church. He lived through extreme racism, segregation, and discrimination. After attending Talladega College while Bull Connor ruled Alabama, he saw no opportunities to advance as a Black man in Alabama or Kentucky, so he joined the military and was stationed in Germany for 20 months. Then he moved to D.C. to attend Howard University and earn a Master of Social Work (MSW) degree. He had a long career in Federal and District government in high-level administrative positions. He has been an activist, leader, and community organizer throughout his life and worked with many civil rights organizations including Robert F. Kennedy (RFK) Foundation, Student Non-Violent Coordinating Committee (SNCC) and Model Cities. He believes that youth activism and grassroots community organizing is only way to address the continuing injustices in our society and he is optimistic about current youth movements. He had a long tenure with the Brookland Literary and Hunting Club (BLAHC) and took over many of the duties of Chairman. BLAHC has been a very important organization for accomplished professional Black men to come together to share support, information, and resources, and, of course, to socialize, and play cards. The organization is now losing membership due to aging. Its future is uncertain.
      James Butts' oral history focuses on his commitment to public service. He speaks about how proud he is of working on the ground as a social worker and having been appointed by three District Mayors to run a government department. His career developed in tandem with social movements and has been motivated by a concern for justice and the lives of society's most vulnerable. He reflects on how attending university in Alabama during segregation and Bull Connor helped to inform his world view. He moved to Washington, D.C. to earn his Master of Social Work (MSW) at Howard University. After beginning a career in service, his work led him to work with the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC). Later he would play a role in founding the Robert F. Kennedy (RFK) Foundation. Butts highlights the 'literary' aspect of the Brookland Literary and Hunting Club. He speaks about the ways that the club has been used as a way to discuss social and political issues. He uses Michelle Alexander's New Jim Crow, which focuses on mass incarceration, as an example of issues that they would speak about. As members aged, the club became a place for members to discuss health related issues.
    - Jock Banks interview, 2018-06-19
      Jock Banks was born on August 11, 1953. He grew up in D.C., went to public schools, and then American University, Law School. He worked as U.S. Attorney in Attorney General's Office. Mr. Banks is married with two grown children.
      Jock Banks reflects on growing up in Washington, D.C. The son of a doctor and a teacher, he considers himself to have had a comfortable middle-class up bring in a house that valued hard work. A lawyer who attended Washington, D.C. public schools then American University, he has seen the city go through many changes. He reflects on demographic shifts, both white flight and the return of white people which made D.C. less of a 'chocolate city'. His parents were both poker players, and his father had been a member of the Brookland Literary and Hunting Club. Poker has been part of his life since an early age. Born in 1953, he is one of the younger members of the Brookland Literary and Hunting Club, which he refers to as 'old man poker'. In the interviews he discusses the history and current demise of the Brookland Literary and Hunting Club Poker Group.
    - Thomas Taylor interview part 1, 2018-05-16
      Called by some colleague the 'godfather of daycare' in the Washington, D.C. area, Thomas Taylor was a social worker, who committed his career to developing programs for children and youth. He was particularly dedicated to improving services for early childhood development. Mr. Taylor was born in New Haven, Connecticut in 1926, then moved to Washington, D.C. at age 16 when he enrolled in high school. He has lived in Washington, D.C., area for over 70 years.
      This interview delves into Thomas Taylor's family history; experiences growing up during segregation; educational experiences; Army service; marriages; family life; and long career as a pioneer in the early childhood education programs of D.C. and the country. Mr. Taylor talks about the founding of the Brookland Literary and Hunting Club poker group and it's members past and present; as well as reflections on health and aging.
    - Thomas Taylor interview part 2, 2018-05-16
    - Wilhelmina Banks interview, 2018-05-03